A Guide to the Misty of Chincoteague Foundation Illustrations ca. 1946-1963
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Misty of Chincoteague Foundation Illustrations ca. 1946-1963
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
11379
ca. 170 illustrations, letter, and other items
The collection consists chiefly of black and white illustrations by Weslye Dennis used in Marguerite Henry's books including Misty of Chincoteague, Sea Star, Orphan of Chincoteague, and Stormy, Misty's Foal. The collection also contains a letter from Henry to Dennis and miscellaneous artwork.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was a gift of the Misty of Chincoteague Foundation, Inc. through Elizabeth H. Sutton of Charlottesville, Virginia, on February 9, 1998.
Scope and Content Information
There are ca. 170 illustrations, ca. 1946-1963, chiefly black and white pencil drawings, by Wesley Dennis (1903-1966), noted author and illustrator of books for children and young adults, used in the following books by Marguerite Henry (1902-1997), Misty of Chincoteague[1947], Sea Star: Orphan of Chincoteague[1949], and Stormy, Misty's Foal[1963]. The collaboration between Henry and Dennis contributed significantly to the popularity of horse books. Misty of Chincoteague is one of the best known and most popular of Dennis' work for young readers. The illustrations by Wesley Dennis are often considered a major contributing factor in making Marguerite Henry's stories classic favorites.
There is also a letter, February 4, 1946, from Marguerite Henry to Wesley Dennis, concerning the autographing party for Misty of Chincoteague and Morgan sketches or other horse illustrations by Dennis to be displayed. Other items include a color poster illustration by Wesley Dennis of "Misty" promoting " Misty of Chincoteague by Marguerite Henry & Illustrated by Wesley Dennis" and a mat board of twelve black-and-white illustrations used chiefly for Stormy, Misty's Foal.
Contents List
- Misty of Chincoteague Foundation, Inc. 1995-1998 (Box 1)
- Misty of Chincoteague Illustrations [1946], 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Illustration on page 1 [1948] (Box 1)
    The Phantom and Misty on half title page
  - Illustration on page 5 [1948] (Box 1)
    "To... all of whom really live on Chincoteague Island.. ." on dedication page
  - Illustration on page 7 [1948] (Box 1)
    Tree branch on contents page
  - Illustration on page 9 [1948] (Box 1)
    Spanish galleon on half title page of part one
  - Illustration on page 10 [1948] (Box 1)
    "A wild, ringing neigh shrilled up from the hold of the Spanish galleon." [page 11]
  - Illustration on page 13 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Meanwhile, in the dark hold of the ship, a small bay stallion was pawing the floor
    of his stall." [page 13]
  - Illustration on page 14-15 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "The stallion neighed encouragement to his mares, who were struggling to keep afloat, fighting the wreckage and the sea." [page 16]
  - Illustration on page 16 [1948] (Box 1)
    Map depicting "... Assateague Beach, that long, sandy island which shelters the tidewater country of Virginia and Maryland." [page 16]
  - Illustration on page 19 [1948] (Box 1)
    "When htey could eat no more, they pawed shallow wells with their hooves for drinking water. Then they rolled in the wiry grass, letting out great whinnies of happiness." [page 19]
  - Illustration on page 21 [1948] (Box 1)
    "On bitter days, when they stood colse-huddled for comfort, each pony could enjoy the warmth of his neighbor's coat as well as his own." [pages 20-21]
  - Illustration on page 23 [1948] (Box 1)
    Buoy on half title page of part two
  - Illustration on page 24 [1948] (Box 1)
    "On a windy Saturday morning, half-past March, a boy and his sister were toiling up the White Hills of Assateague Beach." [page 25]
  - Illustration on page 26 [1948] (Box 1)
    Suddenly the boy [Paul] bent over and picked up a whitened, bow-shaped object. The girl [Maureen] was at his side in an instant." [page 26]
  - Illustration on page 27 [1948] (Box 1)
    "A Spanish galleon... caught in a northeaster." [page 28]
  - Illustration on page 30-31 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "Paul and Maureen fell to the sand... They watched as the stallion herded his family like a nervous parent on a picnic." [page 30]
  - Illustration on page 35 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Pied Piper was overtaking the Phantom." [page 34]
  - Illustration on page 36 [1948] (Box 1)
    "... you can see that the wild critters have 'No Trespassing' signs tacked up on every pine tree." [page 29]
  - Illustration on page 39 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Then he [Grandpa] took off his boots and socks and dug his toes in the sand, like fiddler crabs scuttling for home." [page 38]
  - Illustration on page 42-43 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "Why, she jes' broke the singletree as if 'twas a matchstick, cleared the fence, and blew to her island home with the reins a-stringin' out behind her." [page 42]
  - Illustration on page 45 [1948] (Box 1)
    "It's time we was gettin' back home to Chincoteague, and Grandma's turkeys." [page 45]
  - Illustration on page 47 [1948] (Box 1)
    "... said Paul, as he whisked over the fence... Maureen slipped between the rails and caught up with him." [page 46]
  - Illustration on page 49 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Paul and Maureen flew to Grandpa and hugged him." [page 49]
  - Illustration on page 51 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Paul learned to burrow under the sand with his toes and lift the clam to the surfac... She raked the clams instead with a long wooden rake." [page 51]
  - Illustration on page 54-55 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "From all over the barnyard came wild geese and tame geese, big ducks and little ducks, marsh hens and chicks." [page 53]
  - Illustration on page 56 [1948] (Box 1)
    "They built a manger, spending long moments deciding just how high it should be placed. They scrubbed a rain barrel to be used for a watering trough." [page 55]
  - Illustration on page 60 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Paul loped along slowly to save his mount's strength." [page 61]
  - Illustration on page 62-63 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "The horses were clattering down, each man taking his own." [page 62]
  - Illustration on page 64 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Suddenly Paul saw Wyle Maddox' horse rear into the air." [page 64]
  - Illustration on page 70 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Paul Beebe was bringing in the Phantom and a colt!" [page 70]
  - Illustration on page 76 [1948] (Box 1)
    "The fisherman was trying to get a better view." [page 75]
  - Illustration on page 78-79 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "They plunged into the water, the stallions leading, the mares following, neighing encouragement to their colts." [page 73]
    "The Phantom's got a new colt!... A boy hiding a colt's head above the swirling water." [page 77]
  - Illustration on page 81 [1948] (Box 1)
    "But all the wildness seemed to have ebbed out of the Phantom... Then she carefully straddled her colt, and fenced in the small white body with her own slender legs." [page 80]
  - Illustration on page 82 [1948] (Box 1)
    "The Pied Piper wheeled around Paul... And he pushed Paul out of the way while the crowds laughed hysterically." [page 81-82]
  - Illustration on page 84-85 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "Slowly and dejectedly the wild ponies paraded through the main streets of Chincoteague." [page 85]
  - Illustration on page 87 [1948] (Box 1)
    "At last the procession turned into the pony penning grounds... while children and parents and horse dealers hung over the fence." [pages 86-87]
  - Illustration on page 88 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Suddenly it was Phantom's turn to be herded into the corral." [page 88]
  - Illustration on page 91 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Granpa was in the kitchen, standing before a mirror, trimming the bristles in his ears when Maureen and Paul came in with the groceries." [page 91]
  - Illustration on page 94 [1948] (Box 1)
    "As Paul and Maureen stood inside the big corral, looking at Misty, they knew she was the finest-blooded colt in the world." [page 95]
  - Illustration on page 96 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Slowly he turned his head and came face to face with the Pied Piper." [page 96]
  - Illustration on page 98-99 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "Round and round the pen the colts were plodding, searching for their mothers, flinging their heads up, whimpering, trying to suckle anything their muzzles could reach." [page 99]
  - Illustration on page 101 [1948] (Box 1)
    "The fire chief stood silent and thoughtful. He looked past the grounds and out to the bay, where the masts of the fishing boats formed spider-thin lines against the graying sky." [page 100]
  - Illustration on page 106 [1948] (Box 1)
    "He [Paul] held onto the fence with one hand and made a watershed over his eyes with the other." [page 107]
  - Illustration on page 109 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Slowly, cautiously, hardly daring to breathe, he [Paul] climbed up and over the tailgate and into the truck." [page 108]
  - Illustration on page 110 [1948] (Box 1)
    "And in the occassional flashes of light, he saw the copper-and-white tail of the Phantom sweeping nervously over misty." [page 110]
  - Illustration on page 119 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Finally she [Maureen] climbed the fence and jumped inside the corral. The wild ponies were refreshed by the rain. They thundered past and around her." [page 118]
  - Illustration on page 120 [1948] (Box 1)
    "The Phantom was tugging at a rope tied around Misty's neck. A sold rope!" {page 120]
  - Illustration on page 124-125 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "The ladies of the auxiliary hovered over them anxiously, heaping their plates with oysters and clam fritters, and great helpings of Chincoteague pot pie." [page 125]
  - Illustration on page 126 [1948] (Box 1)
    "And just when he was doffing his cap and bowing to the crowds, the pony tossed him and his cigar and red cap high into the air." [page 127]
  - Illustration on page 128 [1948] (Box 1)
    "They turned around to see a station wagon at the curb, with a man and a small boy in the front seat." [page 128]
  - Illustration on page 137 [1948] (Box 1)
    "She tried standing head-to-tail with Misty, but Misty's tail was so short and floppy that it was not much good." [page 136]
  - Illustration on page 139 [1948] (Box 1)
    "... Paul explained to Grandpa one evening as he and Maureen stood and watched him trim one of his ponies' hooves." [page 138]
  - Illustration on page 141 [1948] (Box 1)
    "When the days grew brisk she [Misty] would gallumph across the hard marsh, then suddenly she would stop stock-still, letting a gull light on her back while her nostrils quivered with excitement." [pages 140-141]
  - Illustration on page 143 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Other times she [Phantom] stood leaning far out over the fence, and there was a wild, sad look about her." [page 143]
  - Illustration on page 145 [1948] (Box 1)
    "There was not much talk while Grandma cut slivers of pink ham, dished up oysters, and ladled hot gravy over the dumplings." [page 144]
  - Illustration on page 148 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Misty grew jealous of the attentions her mother was getting... One time she lifted a hat all covered with roses and dropped it in the water barrel." [page 148]
  - Illustration on page 150-151 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "She [Grandma] and Maureen were hanging up clthes at the time, while Paul, perched on top of a chicken coop, was silently whittling a pole into a clothes prop." [page 150]
  - Illustration on page 153 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Paul and Maureen each took a long, deep breath as they clutched the tiny wishbone that was to decide their fate." [page 153]
  - Illustration on page 156 [1948] (Box 1)
    "But the Phantom was not running a race. She was enjoying herself." [page 157]
  - Illustration on page 161 [1948] (Box 1)
    "With the fence as a mounting block, Maureen swung up behind Paul." [page 160]
  - Illustration on page 162 [1948] (Box 1)
    "All I want is wings on my feet." [page 162]
  - Illustration on page 165 [1948] (Box 1)
    "With one bar down, Maureen put her heels into Phantom's side and Phantom sailed over the hurdle and out upon the marshy plain." [page 164]
  - Illustration on page 166-167 [1948] (Box Oversize Box N-15)
    "It's the Pied Piper!... He's coming to git the Phantom." [page 167]
  - Illustration on page 171 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Misty's quizzical little face with its funny blaze was peering around at them." [page 170]
  - Illustration on page 172 [1948] (Box 1)
    "Reckon I never heard a pony talk up so plain... 'I'm Misty of Chicoteague'.. ." [page 173]
- Sea Star: Orphan of Chincoteague Illustrations [1948], 4 folders (Box 1)
- Misty of Chincoteague by Marguerite Henry, illustrated by Wesley Dennis 1947 (Box 1)
- Sea Star: Orphan of Chincoteague by Marguerite Henry, illustrated by Wesley Dennis 1949 (Box 1)
- Stormy, Misty's Foal Illustrations [1962], 6 folders (Box 2)
- Stormy, Misty's Foal by Marguerite Henry, illustrated by Wesley Dennis 1963 (Box 2)
- Sea Star, Orphan of Chincoteague Illustrations [1948], Oversize folder (14" x 18"): 2 folders (Oversize OS Box N-15)
- Stormy, Misty's Foal Illustrations [1962], Oversize folder (14" x 18") (Oversize OS Box N-15)
- Misty of Chincoteague Illustrations [1946], Oversize folder (19" x 24") (Oversize OS Box N-15)
- Sea Star: Orphan of Chincoteague Illustrations [1948], Oversize folder (19" x 24") (Oversize OS Box N-15)
- Misty of Chincoteague Series Miscellaneous [1946], Oversize folder (19" x 24") (Oversize OS Box N-15)
- Misty of Chincoteague [1947], Color poster illustration (28" x 20") (Oversize OS Tray 39)
  by Wesley Dennis of "Misty" promoting " Misty of Chincoteague by Marguerite Henry & Illustrated by Wesley Dennis."
- Stormy, Misty's Foal [1963], Mat board (48" x 32") (Oversize OS Tray 39)
  with twelve black-and-white illustrations by Wesley Dennis, chiefly for this book